“What？”因素。我们快速评估一下别人怎么看你的
The what factor. Let's do a quick assessment of what other people think of
口音。一天里，有多少次别人会要求你重复一遍？
your accent. How often during a day does someone ask you to repeat yourself? How
说出电子邮件地址要花多久？你又要拼多少次自己的名字？
long does it take to give your email address? And how many times do you have to
这就是你的 what factor。但真正的问题是：这会如何
spell your name? That's your what factor. But the real question is, how does this
影响你？它如何影响你的工作、家庭生活，
affect you? How does it affect your working situation, your home life, your
这会让你感到沮丧吗？还是会鼓励你
life as a whole? Does it make you feel discouraged? Or does it encourage you to
或是让你觉得周围的人都需要改变？
change? Or does it make you feel like everyone else needs to change around you?
我们来讲一个有这种感受的人。我们叫她 Mei Li。一位中国教授
about someone who felt this way. We'll call her Mei Li. A Chinese professor was
在美国学习英语，她的老师建议她为了
studying English in the US and her instructor had suggested that, for
方便，把自己名字的发音美式化。她立刻勃然大怒。
convenience, she Americanized the pronunciation of her name and she flew
她勃然大怒，写了一封长邮件痛斥他，说这件事对她多么不尊重。
into a rage. She excoriated him in a long email about how disrespectful this was to
她五千年中国祖先都受到了冒犯。那位美国老师惊呆了，于是把她转给
5,000 years of her Chinese ancestors. The American instructor was stunned and passed
更上级的老师。资深导师开始了解发生了什么。
her on upstairs. The senior instructor set about finding out what was going on. To
说李博士在语言上非常僵化，都算是说得太轻了。导师
say Dr. Li was linguistically rigid is a profound understatement. The instructor
会问：假设你在 DMV，办事员并不知道你的中国
would ask, but let's say you're at the DMV. The clerk doesn't know from Chinese
祖先。你难道不想让他们第一次就听懂你的名字，
ancestors. Don't you just want them to catch your name the first time and to
并顺利处理业务吗？“不，”她会声明，“这是我的名字。”
process the transaction? No, she would declare, it's my name. The instructor
最终告诉她，他们必须取得突破。
finally told her that they simply had to make a breakthrough. So her entire
家庭作业包括留一条语音留言，把她的名字美式化，
homework would consist of leaving a voicemail with her name Americanized so it
让任何陌生人都更容易听懂。她留下了八到十条
would be easier to understand by any random person. She left eight to 10
听起来仍像中文发音的留言。最后，她留下一条以
identical Chinese sounding attempts. Finally, she left one that started with a
一声深叹和更低沉声音开头的留言：My name is Mei Li。那真是太漂亮了。
deep sigh and a deeper voice. My name is Mei Li. It was a thing of beauty.
Unfortunately, 30 seconds later, she left another very nasal one. My name is Mei Li.